Gerald R. Gill Papers MS170
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
- University service, 1975 -- 2007; MS170.008; 3.6 Linear Feet 3 record cartons.
  - University committees and service, 1975 -- 2006; MS170.008.001; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton.
    - Equal Educational Opportunity Committee, 1988 -- 1989; MS170.008.001.043.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 9)
    - Equal Educational Opportunity Committee, 1988; MS170.008.001.043.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 10)
    - Equal Educational Opportunity Committee, 2003; MS170.008.001.043.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 11)
    - A Study of Trends in Minority Applications, Acceptances, and Enrollment at Tufts University 1972-1984 Part I report, 1985; MS170.008.001.043.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 12)
    - Society Organized Against Racism, 1985 -- 1988; MS170.008.001.043.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 13)
    - Prejudice Educational Options Committee, 1987; MS170.008.001.043.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 14)
    - Committee on Tenure and Promotion, 1988, 1999; MS170.008.001.043.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 15)
    - Faculty events, 1988; MS170.008.001.043.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 16)
    - American Studies Visiting Committee report, 1989; MS170.008.001.043.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 17)
    - Freshman Advising, 1989; MS170.008.001.043.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 18)
    - Faculty memos and correspondence, 1993 -- 1994; MS170.008.001.043.00019; 2 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 19-20)
    - Faculty memos and correspondence, 1994, 1998 - 2003; MS170.008.001.043.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 21)
    - University service correspondence, circa 1994 -- 2005; MS170.008.001.043.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 22)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on the Future Growth of the Religion Department at Tufts, 1995; MS170.008.001.043.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 23)
    - Faculty correspondence and events, 1995; MS170.008.001.043.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 24)
    - African American Center Advisory Committee, 1995 -- 1996; MS170.008.001.043.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 25)
    - Faculty memos and correspondence, 1996 -- 1997; MS170.008.001.043.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 26)
    - Financial Aid and Admissions Committee, 1997; MS170.008.001.043.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 27)
    - Task Force on Race Final Report, 1997 -- 2001; MS170.008.001.043.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 28)
    - Oversight Panel, Task Force on Race report, 1999; MS170.008.001.043.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 29)
    - Oversight Panel, Task Force on Race agenda, 1999; MS170.008.001.043.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 30)
    - Overnight Panel, Task Force on Race correspondence, 1999 -- 2000; MS170.008.001.043.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 31)
    - Overnight Panel, Task Force on Race report, 1999 -- 2000; MS170.008.001.043.00031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 32)
    - Chair of the Academic Standing Committee, 1999; MS170.008.001.043.00032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 33)
    - Faculty awards and correspondence, 2000, 2005 -- 2006; MS170.008.001.043.00033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 34)
    - Faculty memos and correspondence, 2000; MS170.008.001.043.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 35)
    - Faculty review committee, 2000; MS170.008.001.043.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 36)
    - Faculty search manual, 2000; MS170.008.001.043.00036; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 37)
    - Tufts summer session, 2000; MS170.008.001.043.00037; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 38)
      75 years from the date of creation.
    - Restructuring of budget for School of Arts and Sciences notes, circa 2001; MS170.008.001.043.00038; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 39)
    - Faculty memos and meeting agendas, 2002; MS170.008.001.043.00039; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 40)
    - Faculty memos and correspondence, 2002; MS170.008.001.043.00040; 1 Folder(s) (Box 43, Folder 41)
    - Balfour Scholars, 2003; MS170.008.001.044.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 1)
    - Ad Hoc Committee on Faculty Retention, 2004; MS170.008.001.044.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 2)
    - Arts and Sciences Curricula Committee meeting, 2004; MS170.008.001.044.00003; 2 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 3--4)
    - Arts and Sciences Search Advisory Committee, 2004; MS170.008.001.044.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 5)
    - University service correspondence, 2004; MS170.008.001.044.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 6)
    - Faculty memos and correspondence, 2005; MS170.008.001.044.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 7)
    - Arts and Sciences strategic plan for scholarship, circa 2006; MS170.008.001.044.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 8)
    - Pre-major advising survey, 2006; MS170.008.001.044.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 9)
  - Departmental committees and service, 1980 -- 2007; MS170.008.002; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton.
    Sub-series includes agendas and correspondence from the curriculum committee and undergraduate education committee, as well as course evaluations, course offerings, advising materials, and faculty records.
    - Departmental History notes, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.008.002.044.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 10)
    - Department of History course evaluations, 1981 -- 1986; MS170.008.002.044.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 11)
    - Department of History course offerings and evaluations, 1987 -- 1989; MS170.008.002.044.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 12)
    - Department of History course offerings and evaluations, 1988 -- 1989; MS170.008.002.044.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 13)
    - Departmental tenure and promotion report, 1987; MS170.008.002.044.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 14)
    - Faculty information, 1987 -- 1988; MS170.008.002.044.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 15)
    - Faculty information, 1989 -- 1990; MS170.008.002.044.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 16)
    - Faculty information, 1993 -- 1994; MS170.008.002.044.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 17)
    - Faculty information, 1995 -- 1996; MS170.008.002.044.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 18)
    - Faculty information, 1998 -- 1999; MS170.008.002.044.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 19)
    - Faculty information, 1999 -- 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 20)
    - Faculty information, 2000 -- 2002; MS170.008.002.044.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 21)
    - Faculty information, 2002 -- 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 22)
    - Faculty information, 2003 -- 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 23)
    - Faculty information, 2004 -- 2005; MS170.008.002.044.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 24)
    - Faculty information, 2005; MS170.008.002.044.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 25)
    - Faculty memos, 1995, 2002 - 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 26)
    - History courses and newsletter, circa 1996 -- 1997; MS170.008.002.044.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 27)
    - Departmental retreat meeting, 1998; MS170.008.002.044.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 28)
    - Faculty advising, 1998 -- 1999; MS170.008.002.044.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 29)
    - Faculty advising, 1999; MS170.008.002.044.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 30)
    - Faculty advising, 2001 -- 2002; MS170.008.002.044.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 31)
    - Faculty advising, 2002; MS170.008.002.044.00031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 32)
    - Faculty advising, 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 33)
    - Faculty advising, 2006; MS170.008.002.044.00033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 34)
    - Teaching load, 1998 -- 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 35)
    - Visiting Scholar in Korean History correspondence, 1998 -- 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 36)
    - Glenn Buttrick Scholarship Fund, 1999; MS170.008.002.044.00036; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 37)
    - American Studies Faculty meeting, 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00037; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 38)
    - Chairs and Directors Discussion on Interdisciplinary outline, 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00038; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 39)
    - Chinese History search committee correspondence, 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00039; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 40)
    - Department Curriculum Committee, 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00040; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 41)
    - Faculty departures, 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00041; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 42)
    - Letters of recommendation, 2000; MS170.008.002.044.00042; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 43)
    - History department newsletters, 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00043; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 44)
    - Faculty search correspondence, 2001; MS170.008.002.044.00044; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 45)
    - Leave of absence correspondence, 2001 -- 2002; MS170.008.002.044.00045; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 46)
    - Undergraduate Curriculum Committee, 2002; MS170.008.002.044.00046; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 47)
    - Undergraduate Education Committee, 2002 -- 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00047; 2 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 48-49)
    - Undergraduate Education Committee, 2003 -- 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00048; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 50)
    - World Civilizations Sub-Committee, 2002 -- 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00049; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 51)
    - History Society, 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00050; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 52)
    - 1997-2002 History Trends, 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00051; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 53)
    - New Faculty in Arts & Sciences, 2003 -- 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00052; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 54)
    - Rationale for a Joint Tenure-Track Faculty Appointment of an Asian Americanist Between the History Department and the American Studies Program, 2003; MS170.008.002.044.00053; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 55)
    - History meetings, five year plan, and senior survey, 2005; MS170.008.002.044.00054; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 56)
    - History curriculum changes, 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00055; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 57)
    - Letters of recommendation, 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00056; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 58)
    - Prince of Asturias Professor of Hispanic Civilizations correspondence, 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00057; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 59)
    - Senior Survey, 2004; MS170.008.002.044.00058; 1 Folder(s) (Box 44, Folder 60)
    - Departmental correspondence and commencement scripts, 2004 -- 2005; MS170.008.002.045.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 1)
    - Departmental memos, 2005; MS170.008.002.045.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 2)
    - History course list, 2005; MS170.008.002.045.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 3)
    - Departmental forms, memos, and commencement scripts, 2005 -- 2006; MS170.008.002.045.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 4)
    - Departmental memos and correspondence, 2005 -- 2006; MS170.008.002.045.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 5)
    - American Studies Ad Hoc Committee, 2006; MS170.008.002.045.00006; 2 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 6--7)
    - Graduate Program evaluation, 2006; MS170.008.002.045.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 8)
    - Departmental memos and correspondence, 2006; MS170.008.002.045.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 9)
    - Faculty correspondence, 2007; MS170.008.002.045.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 10)
  - Other service, 1987 -- 2005; MS170.008.003; 1.2 Linear Feet 1 record carton.
    Sub-series includes a small amount of material related to Gill's service outside the Tufts community, such as preserving the history of Boston's under-documented communities and reopening the African Meeting House.
    - Black Men's Group, 1987; MS170.008.003.045.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 11)
    - Planning committee in conjunction with the reopening of the African Meeting House, 1987; MS170.008.003.045.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 12)
    - American Studies/ Center for Public Service summer workshop, 1988; MS170.008.003.045.00012; 2 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 13-14)
    - Application for Sabbatical, 1988; MS170.008.003.045.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 15)
    - Faculty workshop on integrating race and gender into the curriculum, 1988; MS170.008.003.045.00014; 2 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 16-17)
    - Study skills workshop for Black students, 1988; MS170.008.003.045.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 18)
    - American Orthopsychiatric annual meeting call for proposals, 1990; MS170.008.003.045.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 19)
    - Ford Foundation Postdoctoral Fellowship for Minorities application, 1990; MS170.008.003.045.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 20)
    - TCU Senate Course evaluation guide, 1995, 2000; MS170.008.003.045.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 21)
    - Ted Shapiro Memorial Scholarship Fund, 1995; MS170.008.003.045.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 22)
    - Against the Tide…Those who Refuse to Fight grant proposal, 1996; MS170.008.003.045.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 23)
    - Advisory Committee, Preserving the History of Boston's under-documented, 1998; MS170.008.003.045.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 24)
    - Advisor's form, 1998; MS170.008.003.045.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 25)
    - Nia project, 1999 -- 2002; MS170.008.003.045.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 26)
    - Nia project, 2000; MS170.008.003.045.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 27)
    - Slam Dunk: A Basketball History of the 20th century project correspondence, 1999 -- 2001; MS170.008.003.045.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 28)
    - Slam Dunk: A Basketball History of the 20th century project correspondence, 2000 -- 2002; MS170.008.003.045.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 29)
    - Slam Dunk: A Basketball History of the 20th century project scripting proposal, 2001; MS170.008.003.045.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 30)
    - Slam Dunk: A Basketball History of the 20th century project scripting proposal writings, circa 2000s; MS170.008.003.045.00028; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 31)
    - Project GYRO Scholar at Boston College, 2000; MS170.008.003.045.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 32)
    - Gregory Hunter Research Scholarship, 2000 -- 2001; MS170.008.003.045.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 33)
    - Tufts Black Alumni Association correspondence, 2002; MS170.008.003.045.00031; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 34)
    - Tufts Black Alumni Association correspondence, 2002 -- 2003; MS170.008.003.045.00032; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 35)
    - 69th University of Connecticut Foreign Policy Seminar, 2002; MS170.008.003.045.00033; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 36)
    - Asian and Latino Studies curriculum petition, 2003; MS170.008.003.045.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 37)
    - Senior fund, 2003; MS170.008.003.045.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 38)
    - Senior survey, 2004; MS170.008.003.045.00036; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 39)
    - Tufts Daily opinion piece, 2002; MS170.008.003.045.00037; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 40)
    - High Table Dinner, 2005; MS170.008.003.045.00038; 1 Folder(s) (Box 45, Folder 41)
- Writings, 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009; 2.9 Linear Feet 2 record cartons and 1 document box
  Writings consist of drafts, correspondence, notes, and writing proposals. Subjects include African American history, African American protest movements, the civil rights movement, pacifism, and Tufts University history.
  This series includes drafts of the books Struggling Yet in Freedom's Birthplace: The Civil Rights Movement in Boston, 1935-1972, and Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, unpublished at the time of Gill's death. The manuscript for Struggling Yet in Freedom's Birthplace is partial, and covers the years 1935-1965.
  Writings also include drafts of the Faculty Guide and Student Study Guide for Eyes on the Prize College Telecourse, and of the text that accompanied the exhibit Another Light on the Hill: A Brief History of African-American Students at Tufts, 1900 – present. Other writings address race relations in Boston, the history of Black athletes at Tufts, the African American Center at Tufts, conservative tendencies in United States politics, youth unemployment, and many other diverse topics.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - Academic Achievements and Sporting Accomplishments: The History of Black Male and Female Athletes at Tufts, 1900-present, draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 1)
  - Affirmative Action at Tufts - A Defense, draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 2)
  - African American National Biography correspondence, 2003; MS170.009.046.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 3)
  - African American Opposition to the War draft, 1991; MS170.009.046.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 4)
  - African American Workers in New England, 1900-1945, draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 5)
  - Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century: Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest manuscript, 1985; MS170.009.047.00001; 1 Volumes (Box 47)
  - Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century: Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest manuscript, 1985; MS170.009.047.00002; 1 Volumes (Box 47)
  - Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century: Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest facsimile, 1985; MS170.009.047.00003; 1 Volumes (Box 47)
  - America is the Black Man's Battleground: Anti-War Activities on Historically Black Colleges and Universities, 1965-1972, draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00006; 3 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 6-8)
  - Another "Light on the Hill": A Brief History of African-American Students at Tufts, 1910-1990, circa 2000s; MS170.009.046.00007; 2 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 9-10)
  - Black Critics of Containment: The Pittsburgh Courier and the Korean War, 1950-1953, circa 1980s; MS170.009.046.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 11)
  - Black Protest in Boston, circa 1990s; MS170.009.046.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 12)
  - Civil Rights in the United States Encyclopedia correspondence, 1999; MS170.009.046.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 13)
  - Compare Kennedy/Lewis speech, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 14)
  - "Concern, Protest and Commitment: Tufts University and the Struggles for Racial Equality and Equal Educational Opportunity, 1950-1975", circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00012; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 15)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapters 1-4, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00013; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 16)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapters 5-7, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00014; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 17)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapters 8 and 9, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00015; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 18)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States Wars' of the Twentieth Century, chapter 10, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00016; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 19)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapter 4 draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00017; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 20)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapter 6 and 7 draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00018; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 21)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century correspondence, 1985 -- 1987; MS170.009.046.00019; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 22)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century proofreading remarks, 1987; MS170.009.046.00020; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 23)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, evaluation report, chapters 6-10, 1995; MS170.009.050.00001; 1 Folder(s) (Box 50, Box 1)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapters 1-3 and 5, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.050.00002; 1 Folder(s) (Box 50, Box 2)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapters 6-8, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.050.00003; 1 Folder(s) (Box 50, Folder 3)
  - Dissent, Discontent and Disinterest: Afro-American Opposition to the United States' Wars of the Twentieth Century, chapters 9 and 10, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.050.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 50, Folder 4)
  - "Education Must Not Simply Teach Work - It Must Teach Life": Scholarship and Educational Attainments Among African Americans, 1900-1954 Phi Beta Kappa address, 2000; MS170.009.046.00021; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 24)
  - Faculty Guide and Student Study Guide for the Eyes on the Prize College Telecourse, 1991; MS170.009.046.00022; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 25)
  - "From Different Ends of the Spectrum: Women in the Civil Rights Movement" draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00023; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 26)
  - From Maternal Pacifism to Revolutionary Solidarity: African-American Women's Opposition to the Vietnam War draft, circa 1990; MS170.009.046.00024; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 27)
  - From Progressive Republican to Independent Progressive: The Political Career of Charlotta A. Bass, 1987; MS170.009.046.00025; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 28)
  - The Lament of a Yankee Fan, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00026; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 29)
  - The Keys to the Kingdom 1974-1980, 1991; MS170.009.046.00027; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 30)
  - Meanness Mania, article, 1981; MS170.008.001.00034; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 35)
  - Meanness Mania, correspondence and clippings, 1980; MS170.008.001.00035; 1 Folder(s) (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - "No Time for Banqueting:" African-American Protests In Boston, 1945-1955, drafts, circa 1990s; MS170.009.046.00028; 3 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 31-33)
  - Race, Faith and Fascism: African-American Religious and Secular Pacifism During World War II, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.046.00029; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 34)
  - The Rightward Drift in America draft, 1981; MS170.009.046.00030; 1 Folder(s) (Box 46, Folder 35)
  - Soliloquy, "Multiculturalism in the Academy", 1992; MS170.009.047.00004; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 4)
  - Southern Freedom Movement and African-American Women draft, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.047.00005; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 5)
  - Speech notes, circa 1980 -- 2007; MS170.009.047.00006; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 6)
  - Struggling Yet "In Freedom's Birthplace": The Civil Rights Movement in Boston 1935-1972 project plan, 1997, undated; MS170.009.047.00007; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 7)
  - Struggling Yet "In Freedom's Birthplace": The Civil Rights Movement in Boston 1935-1972 project plan, 1997 -- 1999, undated; MS170.009.047.00008; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 8)
  - Struggling Yet "In Freedom's Birthplace": The Civil Rights Movement in Boston 1935-1972 project plan and publishing agreement, 1997 -- 1998; MS170.009.047.00009; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 9)
  - Struggling Yet "In Freedom's Birthplace": The Civil Rights Movement in Boston 1955-1965, drafts, circa 1997 -- 1998; MS170.009.047.00010; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 10)
  - Struggling Yet 'In Freedom's Birthplace" correspondence, 2001; MS170.009.047.00011; 1 Folder(s) (Box 47, Folder 11)